<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Android on </title>
    <link>https://nextpertise.net/tags/android/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Android on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 17:38:24 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://nextpertise.net/tags/android/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m cooler than you</title>
      <link>https://nextpertise.net/posts/230427_im_cooler_than_you/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 17:38:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nextpertise.net/posts/230427_im_cooler_than_you/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hah!  I don&amp;rsquo;t really believe that thing about being cooler, but have you ever done a project and just felt &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; pleased with yourself?  I turned my Samsung Galaxy Tab S6 Lite into a Linux tablet/laptop and I&amp;rsquo;m feeling pretty happy.  The actual process isn&amp;rsquo;t that involved, so a little of my self-congratulation is probably undeserved, but the result is stinking cool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-a-linux-device&#34;&gt;What is a Linux device?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get into the work, we need to take a philosophical detour.  I wanted a Linux tablet, but what exactly does that mean?  Android is based on Linux, so isn&amp;rsquo;t Android &amp;ldquo;Linux&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, a &amp;ldquo;Linux desktop&amp;rdquo; involves two components.  The first is a shell (in my case Bash) that support the expected set of tools, like &lt;strong&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;hugo&lt;/strong&gt;.  I was able to create that environment by installing Termux.  A graphical x-environment is suppored with Termux, but you have to use VNC to access it and it seems like trying to use fingers to control an Xfce desktop would be frustrating.  And for what?  Certainly there is some coup to be counted, but I see a desktop as a way to run applications.  I see the Android shell like an alternative DE with it&amp;rsquo;s own app environment.  As long as Android apps can access the files in the Termux environment, then why not use the native graphical environment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Office is available for Android, as is Google Docs.  I can use &lt;strong&gt;Markor&lt;/strong&gt; for markdown files, and of course there is a native Firefox.  I can&amp;rsquo;t find a native version of &lt;strong&gt;VS Code&lt;/strong&gt;, so we&amp;rsquo;ll have to think about that.  Otherwise, a traditional desktop really doesn&amp;rsquo;t move things forward on this tablet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;installing-the-bash-environment&#34;&gt;Installing the Bash Environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://nextpertise.net/230427_Termux.png#floatsmallright&#34; alt=&#34;Termux&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to this effort, I had already installed &lt;a href=&#34;https://f-droid.org&#34;&gt;F-Droid&lt;/a&gt; as an alternative to the Play Store that focuses on FOSS (Free Open Source Software).  Pulling Termux from F-Droid instead of the Play Store is supposed to provide an updated version according to their docs.  I downloaded two apps: &lt;strong&gt;Termux&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Termux:Styling&lt;/strong&gt;.  Termux provides a debian-based Bash environment.  Apt is supported for updates, although the Termux project suggests using &lt;strong&gt;pkg&lt;/strong&gt; for installs.  &lt;strong&gt;Pkg&lt;/strong&gt; automatically runs &amp;ldquo;apt update&amp;rdquo; and finds the right mirror, but is basically a wrapper for apt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Termux creates a home directory at &lt;em&gt;/data/data/com.termux/files/home&lt;/em&gt;.  I was able to install the command line tools I expect, such as &lt;strong&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;hugo&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;openssh&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;python&lt;/strong&gt;.  Android apps are able to read and write into the home directory.  Running a Linux shell via Termux doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any impact on speed (and you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t expect it to).  I found a great article at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.learntermux.tech/2022/06/termux-lsd-install-file-folder-icons-in.html&#34;&gt;Learn Termux&lt;/a&gt; that even walked through installing nerd fonts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was able to use &lt;strong&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt; to pull down a copy of this website from Github.  I could then use &lt;strong&gt;hugo server -D&lt;/strong&gt; to run the dev environment.  Going out to the local Firefox allowed me to connect to http://127.0.0.1:1313 and see the dev page!  I typically use VS Code to write for this site, but at this point I could use &lt;strong&gt;nano&lt;/strong&gt; on bash to edit markdown files or use the Android-native Markor editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;visual-studio-code&#34;&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://nextpertise.net/230427_Code_on_Droid.png#floatsmallright&#34; alt=&#34;VS Code running on Android&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no version of Visual Studio Code for Android.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/coder/code-server&#34;&gt;Code-server&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source version of VS Code that runs in a web page, and given my success with hugo I immediately thought of it as an alternative.  There are a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of instructions online for how to do this, some of them quite complicated, but I ultimately got it to work in a fairly straight-forward way.  In the end, what worked was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;pkg install tur-repo
pkg install code-server
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With code-server installed, you need to edit ~/.config/code-server/config.yaml and set the password.  You can do this using &lt;em&gt;nano&lt;/em&gt; or from an Android text editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start the application using the &lt;strong&gt;code-server&lt;/strong&gt; command.  Once it was up and running, I was able to access the environment at http://127.0.0.1:8080.  One last note - I didn&amp;rsquo;t know the path to my home directory and &lt;strong&gt;code-server&lt;/strong&gt; didn&amp;rsquo;t know what to do with &amp;ldquo;~&amp;rdquo;.  Clicking the &amp;ldquo;files&amp;rdquo; icon (right under the hamburger menu) doesn&amp;rsquo;t have an interactive way to browse until you get into your home directory.  So here it is again: &lt;em&gt;/data/data/com.termux/files/home&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-notes&#34;&gt;Final notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; this setup.  It&amp;rsquo;s a lot of fun to use the device and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to travel with it.  Although the pictures show an on-screen keyboard - which works pretty well if you are comfortable two-finger typing - my slim bluetooth keyboard packs up easily and works great in this environment.  I&amp;rsquo;m running &lt;a href=&#34;https://nextpertise.net/posts/221004_tailscale/&#34;&gt;TailScale&lt;/a&gt; in Android to access my home and Termux can access the VPN addresses without an issue.  In fact, the first screenshot where I am sshing into my desktop was taken remotely.  On the whole, this setup takes advantage of Android for the part it does well but still exposes the power of a Linux shell and I&amp;rsquo;m really pleased with it.  It wasn&amp;rsquo;t that complicated to setup, but I&amp;rsquo;m really happy with the result.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5G Troubleshooting</title>
      <link>https://nextpertise.net/posts/220723_5g_troubleshooting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2022 12:14:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nextpertise.net/posts/220723_5g_troubleshooting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://nextpertise.net/220723_droid_signal.jpg#floatsmallleft&#34; alt=&#34;Signal Strength on Android&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My office sits beside an Interstate and generally the Interstate corridor is one of the best places to find cellular coverage.  Sure enough, we have towers reasonably close to the east and west of the building along the Interstate.  The construction of the buildings, like many office buildings, has a strong steel and concrete &amp;ldquo;core&amp;rdquo; with open office space around the perimeter.    My analysis is that those cores, along with the way the buildings set next to each other, creates 5G/LTE shadows within the buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My buildings are setup along &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; cubicle-farm ideas.  To get a feel for where the dead zones are, I got readings on signal strength using my phone at all the cube row intersections.  Wireless signal strength is denoted in decibel-milliwats (dBm).  A decibel is a comparison of two numbers, with a 10dB difference translating as a 10 fold increase.  A 100x difference would be 20dB.  dBm compare a signal to a milliwat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For LTE, signals weaker than -85dB are poor service.  5G uses newer radios and can do pretty well down to -105dB.  T-Mobile, through the acquisition of Sprint, uses low and high bands (800 MHz, 1.9 GHz, and 2.5 GHz) and the lower frequencies penetrate obstructions better (remember how Nextel used to work everywhere?).  Verizon and AT&amp;amp;T use higher frequencies and don&amp;rsquo;t penetrate building interiors as well.  Work uses Verizon, so helps explain the reception issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;determing-5g-signal-strength&#34;&gt;Determing 5G signal strength&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Android, you can find signal strength under &lt;em&gt;Settings &amp;gt; About Phone &amp;gt; Status &amp;gt; SIM card status&lt;/em&gt;.  In my testing this display updated dynamically, so I could just leave it up and walk around.  In the example pictured, my signal strength is -91dB on my LTE phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On an IOS device, dial &lt;em&gt;3001#12345#&lt;/em&gt;.  This brings up some technician information.  Go to the second tab and choose &lt;em&gt;RAT &amp;gt; Serving Cell Info&lt;/em&gt;.  The signal strength is labeled &lt;strong&gt;RSRP&lt;/strong&gt;.  In my experience, this display updates over minutes.  If readings are needed faster, just redial the number to refresh the display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://nextpertise.net/220723_IOS4.jpg#floatsmallright&#34; alt=&#34;Signal Strength on IOS-2&#34;&gt;  &lt;img src=&#34;https://nextpertise.net/220723_IOS3.jpg#floatsmallright&#34; alt=&#34;Signal Strength on IOS-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understand there are apps that measure signal strength, but this was a pretty basic setup and I was fine was a more ad hoc approach.  It seems like every app is a new way to track or show ads anyway, and this prevented yet another app on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pico-cells&#34;&gt;Pico Cells&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My office purchased &amp;ldquo;pico cells&amp;rdquo; - devices that produce a 5G signal over a small indoor area and transmit the traffic over your network to the provider.  I positioned these on the opposite sides of the building that face cell towers and stuck the 5G &amp;ldquo;hockey puck&amp;rdquo; in the window.  The pico cells made an impressive difference.  Close by, my signal went from -110dBm to -65dBm and the zone that received better than -100 dBm extended out about 60 meters.  I repeated the measurement to ensure I had good coverage and here I noticed that the phones tended to be &amp;ldquo;sticky&amp;rdquo; to a particular cell.  Notice in the screen shot that the cellular tower ID is identified.  Intuitively, one might expect the phone to &amp;ldquo;flip&amp;rdquo; to the next tower as soon as the signal was better but what I saw was that the phone tended to keep a tower until it&amp;rsquo;s signal got very weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the cellID will be useful if we have user coverage complaints.  Each of the picocells reported a different ID and I noted those in our recordds so we can trace issues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disabling RCS on Android</title>
      <link>https://nextpertise.net/posts/220328_rcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2022 17:22:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nextpertise.net/posts/220328_rcs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://nextpertise.net/disable_chat.jpg#floatsmallright&#34; alt=&#34;Disabling Chat&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;googles-move-to-rcschat&#34;&gt;Google&amp;rsquo;s move to RCS/Chat&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You really shouldn&amp;rsquo;t care about Google&amp;rsquo;s supported messaging app.  They certainly don&amp;rsquo;t.  They change ideas about messaging more often then their underwear.  Still, they&amp;rsquo;ve made a move from SMS to RCS recently and they&amp;rsquo;re taking you along with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SMS is about thirty years old.  It allows 160 character messages and has features built in to support carrier billing.  Despite it&amp;rsquo;s limitations, it&amp;rsquo;s become the default way to communicate for a certain portion of the population and a part of nearly everyone&amp;rsquo;s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple has led the way in showing the limitations of SMS with their chat app.  SMS is run by the carriers, who have seen it as a cash-cow and not an area for innovation.  Apple didn&amp;rsquo;t try to shoe-horn their offering onto SMS, they built a whole new IP-based application.  Apple added in features like end-to-end encryption for privacy, read receipts, activity indicators, and high-res photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google has recently been shamed for the poor state of messaging on Android and as a result has tried to create an alternative to iMessage around RCS.  Google&amp;rsquo;s take on RCS is called Chat, and there&amp;rsquo;s a protocol built out to support the new service.  Chat takes up many of the improvements that iMessage (and others) have brought to messaging - things like read receipts, activity indicators, and integration with video.  It &lt;em&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; include support for end-to-end encryption.  I&amp;rsquo;ve heard this is in development, but I&amp;rsquo;m suspecious that the carriers are loath to give up access to the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;should-you-care&#34;&gt;Should you care?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://nextpertise.net/digits_app.png#floatsmallleft&#34; alt=&#34;Digits&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No.  As mentioned, if this effort fails it will become the new cherry on the pile of failed messaging apps from Google.  If it succeeds, it will work like Slack/iMessage/etc and you won&amp;rsquo;t really think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a bit of a unique case.  My personal phone is an S9 and I have a seperate work phone.  My personal carrier, T-Mobile, has a DGITS app that carries your T-Mobile phone number to another device via IP.  So I have the DIGITS app on my work phone and only have to carry one phone.  DIGITS supports voice and text - SMS texts.  I leave my personal phone turned on at my desk at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disabling-chat&#34;&gt;Disabling Chat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been missing texts in DIGITS that come to the old phone.  It didn&amp;rsquo;t make sense until I spoke to a close friend (Hi Mike!) and he mentioned RCS and speculated that since I was missing his texts maybe my app didn&amp;rsquo;t support it.  He tested by turning off RCS when communicating with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this leads to my current theory: when users message my personal number, my home phone negotiates chat and receives the message, leaving my DIGITS app out of the loop.  I&amp;rsquo;ve resolved this by going into my personal phone and turning off &amp;ldquo;chat&amp;rdquo; and forcing it to use SMS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, open the (Google) messages app and choose the three vertical dots to find the settings.  Under settings, choose &lt;em&gt;chat features&lt;/em&gt;.  That brings you to the options shown on the left.  The first option - Enable chat features - is the one that disables the chat protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a solution for folks that have two places to receive texts, which is a small group.  It&amp;rsquo;s not a bad tradeoff.  I don&amp;rsquo;t really care about longer bodies of texts or the little blinking activity indication.  If Chat supported end-to-end encryption I might reconsider and hopefully DIGITS will support chat before I have to make that choice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
