<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About Nextpertise on </title>
    <link>https://nextpertise.net/contributors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About Nextpertise on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 11:38:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://nextpertise.net/contributors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Brent Stewart</title>
      <link>https://nextpertise.net/contributors/brent-stewart/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 11:38:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nextpertise.net/contributors/brent-stewart/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-brent-stewart&#34;&gt;About Brent Stewart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been in the IT industry for about 30 years. Early in my career, I benefitted enormously from a knowledgeable mentor. I&amp;rsquo;ve found that my default approach to a lot of my career has been to teach, whether I&amp;rsquo;m part of a team, leadership, working with clients, or explaining things to management. I hope that I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to mentor others along the way and &amp;ldquo;pay it forward.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s in Physics and a Masters in Computer Science / Information Security. I&amp;rsquo;ve written numerous books, mostly for Cisco Press. I&amp;rsquo;ve included links below to the ones still in print. I&amp;rsquo;ve been employed as an IT Director and I&amp;rsquo;ve included my LinkedIn profile below - feel free to link to me and please mention that you saw my website!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My professional interests include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Networking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtualization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automation and Cloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My PCs all run Linux (mostly Ubuntu variants) and I work with and contribute to GNS3, so those topics will come up on this site. On a personal note, I&amp;rsquo;ve been married 24 years and have four kids!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Myron Estibeiro</title>
      <link>https://nextpertise.net/contributors/myron-estibeiro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 11:38:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nextpertise.net/contributors/myron-estibeiro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-myron-estibeiro&#34;&gt;About Myron Estibeiro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been in the IT industry for about 10 years.  I started my career fresh out of college as an intern in a global Network Operations Center (NOC), subsequently moving into a Security Operations Center (SOC) role. There I found my actual &amp;rsquo;taste&amp;rsquo;, which was for Information Security. Throughout my career, I&amp;rsquo;ve had the priviliege of being mentored and guided by some of the finest people in the industry. Equiped with this knowledge and experience, my next goal is to return it back to community via education and consulting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in Engineering (B.E) in Information Technology, with over 10 different industry certifcations under my belt. I&amp;rsquo;m very passionate about problem solving, automating boring and manual stuff with Python, and very enthused in teaching and knowledge sharing - Below is my reference to LinkedIn. Feel free to add me in your professional network and please mention that you saw this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My professional interests include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vulnerability &amp;amp; Risk Management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DevOps and Automation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Malware Analysis &amp;amp; Reverse Engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data &amp;amp; Information Analytics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My systems run on a mix of OS, most of which are virtualized. While I&amp;rsquo;m a techie by day, I&amp;rsquo;m a musician by night; so, check me out on YoutTube and on all other major streaming platforms too!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
