<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>VMWare on </title>
    <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/tags/vmware/</link>
    <description>Recent content in VMWare on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 12:54:46 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.nextpertise.net/tags/vmware/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Deploying a WIM Image to VMWare</title>
      <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/220122_deploying_wim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 12:54:46 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/220122_deploying_wim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Work uses Windows, but I need a Linux workstation with that set of tools.  I find WSL2 incomplete . . . partly because my personal workflow is Linux based.  I spoke with the Windows expert and we agreed to use VMWare Workstation to deploy my Windows environment alongside my Linux system.  Deploying the standard Windows image to a remote VMWare environment wasn&amp;rsquo;t something we had setup already.  Since I&amp;rsquo;m trying to be a special case, he sent me the WIM file to figure out how to deploy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-the-heck-is-a-wim&#34;&gt;What the heck is a WIM?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A WIM is a file-based Windows Image that is made to be easy to test and deploy.   It&amp;rsquo;s kind of like a ZIP, to my understanding, in that it captures all the files and the directory structure of a partition in a file.  Being file-based makes it easy to modify (more on this later).  Because it&amp;rsquo;s not a sector-by-sector image you can deploy it to different sized drives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-dont-you-deploy-it&#34;&gt;How don&amp;rsquo;t you deploy it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/fogserver.png#floatsmallleft&#34; alt=&#34;Fog Project&#34;&gt;
I tried several approaches to using the WIM file.  I&amp;rsquo;ll mention them briefly here so that you can learn from my experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing I tried was making a Windows VM using the Windows 10 downloadable &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/software-download/windows10ISO&#34;&gt;disk image&lt;/a&gt; from Microsoft. Once booted, I added a drive and expanded the WIM to the new drive.  I deleted my drive with generic Windows and rebooted.  I think this didn&amp;rsquo;t work because the new disk wasn&amp;rsquo;t set as a primary partition.  This approach may be doable, but I moved on pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next thing I tried was to deploy it via netboot using a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FOGProject/fogproject&#34;&gt;Fog Server&lt;/a&gt;.  That project is pretty stinking cool!  I was able to get a VM to reference the server for boot information.  The problem here was that I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what it was looking for (first time with PXE).  When I decided it wanted an ISO, I thought &amp;ldquo;if I knew how to convert to the WIM to an ISO, I could just boot that directly in the VM!&amp;rdquo; and abandoned the Fog Server approach.  I may come back to this to learn more about PXE booting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-do-you-deploy-wim&#34;&gt;How do you deploy WIM?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has a series of articles that you&amp;rsquo;ll need to read to understand how to do this.  I&amp;rsquo;ve referenced them, but be warned that they reference each other circlically and there&amp;rsquo;s not a good starting point.  To help you, I&amp;rsquo;m going to attempt to draw a straight line through how &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; accomplished this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1---build-a-winpe-dvd-image&#34;&gt;1 - build a WinPE DVD Image&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to boot into a &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-hardware/manufacture/desktop/winpe-intro?view=windows-11&#34;&gt;WinPE&lt;/a&gt; environment to deploy the WIM image.   Windows PE is a small OS made to facilitate installation, used by Windows as a &amp;ldquo;pre-boot&amp;rdquo; environment.  To build your WinPE boot disk, download the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-hardware/get-started/adk-install&#34;&gt;Windows Assessment and Deployment Kit&lt;/a&gt; on a Windows PC and install the ADK executable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start the &lt;strong&gt;Deployment and Imaging Tools Environment&lt;/strong&gt; as an administrator and create a working set of files using the &lt;strong&gt;copype&lt;/strong&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;copype amd64 C:\WinPE_amd64
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation says you can build an ISO now.  &lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t!&lt;/strong&gt;  There are some batch files that will make this easier - download a zip from &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-hardware/manufacture/desktop/oem-deployment-of-windows-desktop-editions-sample-scripts?preserve-view=true&amp;amp;view=windows-10#apply-image&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and pull the scripts out and place them in the root of your WinPE directory.  Also, grab the WIM file that you&amp;rsquo;re trying to deploy and stick that in the WinPE directory as well.  Now you can build the ISO using the &lt;strong&gt;MakeWinMedia&lt;/strong&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;MakeWinPEMedia /ISO C:\WinPE_amd64 C:\WinPE_amd64\Acme_Installer.iso
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That should create an ISO that&amp;rsquo;s about a half-gig larger than the WIM file.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/tpm.png#floatsmallright&#34; alt=&#34;TPM&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2---build-a-blank-vm-and-enable-secure-boot&#34;&gt;2 - Build a blank VM and enable Secure Boot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created an empty VM with an empty hard drive.  The critical piece here is that my image expects to be deployed to a TPM environment.  TPM requires UEFI and that the VM be encrypted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/vmsetup.png#floatsmallright&#34; alt=&#34;VM Configuration&#34;&gt;
In VMWare Workstation, enable UEFI under Virtual Machine Settings: go to the Options tab, select Advanced, and set the Firmware type to UEFI and Enable Secure Boot.  This is shown in the picture to the right.  While at the Options tab, select Access Control, click the button to encrypt the virtual machine, and choose a password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next add the Trusted Platform Module.   Add it under the Hardware tab by clicking the Add button at the left-bottom of the window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we need the new VM to boot from the ISO we created earlier.  Add the new WinPE ISO to the CD drive and make sure it&amp;rsquo;s marked connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3---boot-winpe-and-deploy-the-image&#34;&gt;3 - Boot WinPE and deploy the image&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we&amp;rsquo;re ready to install the WIM image!  Boot the new VM using the WinPE boot disk.  It will boot to a prompt.  The procedure here is laid out by &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-hardware/manufacture/desktop/capture-and-apply-windows-using-a-single-wim?view=windows-11&#34;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;.  Use the scripts that you added to the boot disk to first help partition the drive and then to apply the image.  &lt;em&gt;CreatePartition-UEFI.txt&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ApplyImage.bat&lt;/em&gt; were included in those scripts.  Obviously image names will change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;diskpart /s CreatePartitions-UEFI.txt
D:\ApplyImage.bat D:\Images\ACME-Standard.wim
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ApplyImage batch file will ask a few questions you need to be prepared for.  You can safely answer &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo; to all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be asked if you want to create a recovery partition.  Recovery Partitions are a great tool, but I want to keep this VM as small as possible and I&amp;rsquo;ll setup recovery mechanisms at the VM level, so I answered no.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you want a compact OS install?  This runs the OS from compressed files, saving a lot of disk space.  Of course, everything has to be uncompressed to be run, so it will slow things down and might take more memory.  Even though I want a small VM, I chose to not install it as a compressed OS because I want to have good performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the WIM file have extended attributes? I&amp;rsquo;m not a Windows guy, but I chose &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo; and everything was fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this point, the VM will go through a preliminary setup, doing things like setting the keyboard type.  It will reboot, ask you to login, and then continue the higher level (Cortana led) part of setup.  From here, everything should install as you would expect!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an interesting side-note, the WinPE boot disk includes an FTP client.  That might be useful script out some additional file copies to the new machine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PSA VMWare</title>
      <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/220105_psa_vmware/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 17:49:07 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/220105_psa_vmware/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;public-service-annoucement-on-vmware-workstation&#34;&gt;Public Service Annoucement on VMWare Workstation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a little dramatic, but I have had a fit with VMWare Workstation and want to pass along what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned.  I recently upgraded my desktop and VMWare performance went in the dump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;backstory&#34;&gt;Backstory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m running Pop!_OS 21.10 using kernel 5.15.  I&amp;rsquo;m using VMWare Workstation 16.2.1 (latest as of early January 2022).  Since I do a lot with virtualization, I have 64GB of RAM.  I was running a Gen 6 i7 and recently upgraded my processor and motherboard to get to gen 12.  Wow! What a difference!  Everything runs super-fast, but VMWare suddenly became anemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;whatd-i-do-to-fix-it&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;d I do to fix it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workstation has trouble running on recent kernels.  Michal Kubeček maintains a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mkubecek/vmware-host-modules&#34;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; with kernel patches.  Download the patch from GitHub - instructions are included in the repository.  You&amp;rsquo;ll know this worked because VMWare boots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ultimate fix was to tell VMware not to swap memory, since I have plenty.  To do this, run Workstation as root:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo -i vmware
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;strong&gt;Edit&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Preferences&lt;/strong&gt; and under &amp;ldquo;Memory&amp;rdquo; select &amp;ldquo;Fit all virtual machine memory into reserved host RAM&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/220105_VMWS_Memory.png&#34; alt=&#34;VMWare Workstation Settings&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I searched all over the Internet and tried a dozen different things to fix this.  I know this is a short article, but I wanted to make sure that others had a less frustrating time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VMWare File Transfer Options including SFTP </title>
      <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/210110_vmware-sftp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 16:51:18 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/210110_vmware-sftp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/210110_VMWare-SFTP.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;VMWare SFTP&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to be upgrading my home VMware server and need to backup the VMs.  My server uses ESXi 6.5 and I&amp;rsquo;ll need to backup the files before upgrading.  Longtime readers may recall that I&amp;rsquo;m using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/200804_homebackup&#34;&gt;Backblaze&lt;/a&gt; to backup the &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; on my server.  That is going swimmingly so far.  I want to backup the images so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to rebuild the VMs after this is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;admin-interface&#34;&gt;Admin interface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to accomplish this is to login to the admin web portal and export the VMs.  Under each VM, go to Actions &amp;gt; Export and this queues downloading the component files.  Exporting over HTTP is slow though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;vmware-workstation&#34;&gt;VMWare Workstation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second option is to backup from VMWare Workstation.  I prefer using this to manage server VMs anyway.  First, connect to the server under &lt;em&gt;File&amp;gt;Connect to Server&lt;/em&gt;.  Once the server is attached to workstation and you can see the VMs, right click a machine and choose &lt;em&gt;Manage &amp;gt; Download&lt;/em&gt;. This is also fairly slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-ssh-with-vmware&#34;&gt;Using SSH with VMWare&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/210110_Filezilla.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Filezilla to VMWare&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To speed up the action, I wanted to grab the VMDKs directly from the server using SFTP.  To set this up, login to the administrative interface of ESXi and look under &amp;ldquo;Host&amp;rdquo;.  Choose &amp;ldquo;Actions&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Enable SSH&amp;rdquo;. SFTP is a part of SSH, so this also enables SFTP.  This isn&amp;rsquo;t the best way to grab the backup, since it will take a little work to stand these up again, but it is faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make this super easy, I used Filezilla.  Under the site manager, I selected SFTP, entered the IP address, and username.  When connecting, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to accept the host key and navigate to /vmfs/volumes/YOUR_VOLUME_NAME/ and each of the VMs will have a directory.  You can also easily upload images this way - ISOs can be saved to to VMWare easily this way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
