<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>VMWare on </title>
    <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/tags/vmware/</link>
    <description>Recent content in VMWare on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 16:51:18 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.nextpertise.net/tags/vmware/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>VMWare File Transfer Options including SFTP </title>
      <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/210110_vmware-sftp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 16:51:18 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/210110_vmware-sftp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/210110_VMWare-SFTP.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;VMWare SFTP&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to be upgrading my home VMware server and need to backup the VMs.  My server uses ESXi 6.5 and I&amp;rsquo;ll need to backup the files before upgrading.  Longtime readers may recall that I&amp;rsquo;m using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/200804_homebackup&#34;&gt;Backblaze&lt;/a&gt; to backup the &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; on my server.  That is going swimmingly so far.  I want to backup the images so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to rebuild the VMs after this is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;admin-interface&#34;&gt;Admin interface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to accomplish this is to login to the admin web portal and export the VMs.  Under each VM, go to Actions &amp;gt; Export and this queues downloading the component files.  Exporting over HTTP is slow though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;vmware-workstation&#34;&gt;VMWare Workstation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second option is to backup from VMWare Workstation.  I prefer using this to manage server VMs anyway.  First, connect to the server under &lt;em&gt;File&amp;gt;Connect to Server&lt;/em&gt;.  Once the server is attached to workstation and you can see the VMs, right click a machine and choose &lt;em&gt;Manage &amp;gt; Download&lt;/em&gt;. This is also fairly slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-ssh-with-vmware&#34;&gt;Using SSH with VMWare&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/210110_Filezilla.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Filezilla to VMWare&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To speed up the action, I wanted to grab the VMDKs directly from the server using SFTP.  To set this up, login to the administrative interface of ESXi and look under &amp;ldquo;Host&amp;rdquo;.  Choose &amp;ldquo;Actions&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Enable SSH&amp;rdquo;. SFTP is a part of SSH, so this also enables SFTP.  This isn&amp;rsquo;t the best way to grab the backup, since it will take a little work to stand these up again, but it is faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make this super easy, I used Filezilla.  Under the site manager, I selected SFTP, entered the IP address, and username.  When connecting, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to accept the host key and navigate to /vmfs/volumes/YOUR_VOLUME_NAME/ and each of the VMs will have a directory.  You can also easily upload images this way - ISOs can be saved to to VMWare easily this way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
