<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Leadership on </title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/leadership/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Leadership on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 16:00:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/leadership/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Blameless Post Mortems</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/221117_postmortems/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 16:00:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/221117_postmortems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you support IT infrastructure, the goal is to minimize issues (particularly issues with big impacts).  Some issues can be anticipated and pre-mitigated.  Considerable success can be achieved but &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; is not for this life.  As a leader, I want to ensure that we learn and improve from every issue.  One way to do that is through a &lt;em&gt;post-mortem&lt;/em&gt; process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a mish-mash of approaches that I used from reading Atul Gwande.  If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read his books, I am amazed at how the stories of the history of surgical improvements can be applied to IT and highly recommend them (a good one to start with is &lt;em&gt;The Checklist Manifesto&lt;/em&gt;).  I was inspired to strengthen and standardize the use of post-mortems from a presentation given by Data Dog at an AWS conference.  This article describes my experiences.  I&amp;rsquo;ve also linked to an excellent article from Data Dog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;history-of-post-mortems&#34;&gt;History of Post-Mortems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of a Morbidity and Mortality conference originated with Ernest Codman, who worked at Massachusetts General in the early 1900s.  It should be noted that the idea of reviewing the mistakes of peers was not initially well received.  Their use over time has helped to instill best-practices, avoid repeating errors, and driven increasing success in patient care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These conferences are held regularly at most hospitals.  At the meeting, selected cases are presented by the responsible doctor.  They lay out the details of the case, approach used, and progression of symptoms.   M&amp;amp;M is particularly good at building accountability and drawing out errors in process and communication.  This process is so integral and well respected as a part of medicene that the presentations and discussion are not legally &amp;ldquo;discoverable&amp;rdquo; in most states to allow doctors to freely discuss these cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Transportation Safety Board (NTSB) and Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) use a similar approach when investigating a airplane crash.  Information and timeliens are assembled, involved parties interviewed, and the conclusions are fed back to the community.  This has led to a drop in annual fatalities from 6.15 (1965) to 2.11 (2010) per 100,000 flight hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-post-mortems-in-an-it-setting&#34;&gt;Using Post-Mortems in an IT setting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, blameless post-mortems should be incorporated into weekly meetings (although events with large impacts usually require a seperate discussion).  I ask the ticket lead to present the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Blameless&amp;rdquo; is a big part of success - I have found that, while no one enjoys being second guessed, most folks want to do good work and that they embrace the accountability, support, and forgiveness of their teammates.  They want to improve and not repeat a bad experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to recognize carelessness and sloppy work with consequences.  This is a critical part of leadership - &lt;strong&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not what you say, it&amp;rsquo;s what you tolerate&lt;/strong&gt;.  When that&amp;rsquo;s the case, folks may need to be assigned a mentor, work on less challenging projects, or even be reassigned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally however, these discussions will find some flaky piece of tech that - when mixed with process confusion and communication issues - leads to fiasco.  When that&amp;rsquo;s the case, the team owns identifying the technical workaround and suggesting process improvements and leadership owns ensuring that those suggestions are carried out and adhered to.  Done well, this process builds ownership and accountability to each other within a team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve found that teams can process a limited number of these, so I select interesting cases for review.  Certainly every SEV1 needs to be reviewed - I typically do that in a dedicated meeting and it leads to a full Reason for Outage (RFO) document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;weekly-reviews&#34;&gt;Weekly Reviews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to review everything at first, but that got impractical and frankly repetitive.  These days, I try to pick three cases that might lead to interesting discussions in weekly meetings.  The idea here is to catch issues before they have a big impact.  I forewarn the implicated people so that they can prepare, and I ask them to consider four lines of questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happened?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Response&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deltas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve found that I can do this &amp;ldquo;short version&amp;rdquo; with each event taking about 5 minutes.  I document the answers to those four questions in my meeting notes so that we can refer back to them later, if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rfos&#34;&gt;RFOs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For RFOs, I usually ask the lead person to write up a report using the bullets above as sections, although we can combine events and response on a timeline.  The report usually settles everyone down and helps establish that the response is under control.  This report needs to be more formal and the areas are probed much deeper.  To help with that, here&amp;rsquo;s an expanded interogative version of those four areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened?  How did we learn of the issue(and should that be automated)?  Did we get the right metrics?  A timeline is useful, and email and IM are helpful resources to get times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How did we respond?  Did it go well?  What was the impact?  How did we communicate?  Communication in the event and after the event is usually the difference between it being classified as a fiasco or learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What resolved the situation?  Did we follow the appropriate processes?  If yes, were they effective?  If no, why not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What needs to change going forward?  Note that this might be directly related to the issue or just something that was noticed in the process (like labeling to make response faster).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;review&#34;&gt;Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process, to be successful, requires a commitment to follow-up on the findings and drive them to conclusion.  The conclusion of some may be that risk has to be communicated and accepted (for instance, where capital isn&amp;rsquo;t available to purchase new equipment).  Many conclusions, as previously mentioned, will be around tecnique, process, and communication and they are absolutely addressable.  I typically put all the reports into a shared directory or repository and review them as a team periodically.  I also add specific  follow-ups as tickets (and note the ticket number in the RFO), so that the team has integrity about following through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;its-about-team-improvement&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about team improvement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the punch line: it&amp;rsquo;s about growing the capability of the people you work with.  For this to work (for me at least), it has to come from a place of good will.  That is frankly difficult when things go pear-shaped.  Leadership has to believe in the team, support the team, and want to see that team succeed.  There is certainly a time to deal with underperforming members, but this is not that time.  Focus on the problem, then focus on never having that problem again, then focus on the confidence and preparedness of the team so that they are ready for whatever comes next.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wisdom in 17 sayings</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/221115_leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 14:41:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/221115_leadership/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I grab onto quotes.  Some I hold onto long enough to consider and they pop up in conversation at odd times.  Others seem to bubble up consistently.  To me, these favorite quotes are the compass that I use to retain my sense of direction in difficult times and circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Folks who have worked with me over the years will have heard versions of these sayings (and probably some that I am forgetting right now).  Some may complain for hearing them too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m preparing for a new job and thinking about how I want to approach new responsibilities.  I&amp;rsquo;ve never tried to compile a list but it&amp;rsquo;s a good time for reviewing these touchstones.  I wanted to share that list with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here are sixteen sayings pertinent to leadership, collected over about that many years of leading.  I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to organize these into themes.  I&amp;rsquo;ve researched attribution and exact quote where possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;general&#34;&gt;General&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sayings can be employed in a variety of circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heard this first while teaching computer networking at Camp Lejeune.  I was told it was an &amp;ldquo;old Marine Corps saying&amp;rdquo;, which I suppose is like the Klingons talking about Shakespeare &amp;ldquo;in the original Klingon&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t know where you&amp;rsquo;re going, any road will get you there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lewis Carroll&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a wonderful boss in the early &amp;rsquo;teens.  He coached me on promotions and, as best I remember, here&amp;rsquo;s his advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to be promoted, take responsiblity.  Being responsible attracts opportunities, and eventually someone in management will say &amp;ldquo;get that guy a hat&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Phelan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I first heard this last one from &lt;strong&gt;12 Rules for Life&lt;/strong&gt; by Jordan Peterson.  The metaphor, about self-discipline and being in control of yourself and your emotions, struck a chord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you get hurt, say, by an arrow, that is pain. . .  However, there is a second arrow, which is your reaction to the arrow, the getting angry, the planning revenge, this is beyond pain, this is suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buddhist saying&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;on-preparation&#34;&gt;On Preparation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, we&amp;rsquo;d anticipate possible issues and make plans to mitigate.  These quotes deal with the issues and rewards of being ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These start with some cynical reminders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad security looks just like good security until seriously attacked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bruce Schneier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and one of my favorites in the same vein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a plan until they get hit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mike Tyson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two of my former CIOs gave me solid advice about preparation that I&amp;rsquo;ve carried forward in my career.  Mike said the first when talking about the constraints of budgeting, but it&amp;rsquo;s a good reminder to not over-commit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can only fit 5 lbs of sugar into a 5 lb bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mike Cross&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kap intimidated me in those days and I regret not getting to know him better.  He had a very clear vision about the way the world works, illustrated below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play the cards you&amp;rsquo;ve got in your hand, not the ones you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kap Kim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saved the best for last.  I use this to encourage preparation and to commend it&amp;rsquo;s results.  I saw Gregg Easterbrook attribute this to Bear Bryant in a Tuesday Morning Quaterback article, but it turns out the original quote is from Neyland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gentlemen, touchdowns follow blocking as sure night follows day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General Robert Neyland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I recall, Easterbrook added the aside that &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;s a lot of fun to run a hundred yards when everyone in front of you is on their back.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;on-troubleshooting&#34;&gt;On Troubleshooting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Troubleshooting requires deep understanding.  It is often denigrated, but I&amp;rsquo;ve always found it to require tremendous imagination and to reward patience and persistence.  I&amp;rsquo;ve had many opportunities to mentor troubleshooting over the years and here are some of my favorite aphorisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first was one of Dad&amp;rsquo;s favorites.  As it has become well known, it&amp;rsquo;s grown a little trite but still makes a great point for technologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you only have a hammer, you tend to see every problem as a nail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abraham Maslow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many times the way forward is not clear.  Here I took an example from being a parent.  This has always been solid advice because there&amp;rsquo;s always some technical cruft that can be cleared up and the act of cleaning either reveals the issue or puts the person in the right headspace.  Although Peterson has a similar saying, mine preceeded his.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My kids would ask me if I&amp;rsquo;ve seen their favorite toy.  I&amp;rsquo;d say, &amp;ldquo;No, but I bet if you clean your room you&amp;rsquo;ll find it&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brent Stewart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one likes change, but sometimes troubleshooting presents opportunities to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You never let a serious crisis go to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rohm Emmanuel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;on-people&#34;&gt;On people&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of these, such as the &amp;ldquo;second arrow&amp;rdquo; also address dealing with other people.  These are the two best quotes I have specifically on the topic of the trials of co-workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My father could be pithy and a little cynical, but he understood something about people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you went to the mall and gave out $20 bills at the door, someone would compain that you didn&amp;rsquo;t have change or were at the wrong door.  You cannot make everyone happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bill Stewart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve carried around this quote since I was a kid.  I think I picked it up from reading Robert Heinlein.  It, or something like it, has been said in various forms for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never attribute to malice what can be adequately explained by stupidity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hanlon&amp;rsquo;s razor, perhaps a restatement from Winston Churchill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extreme Ownership&lt;/strong&gt; as a book is like a Mel Brooks movie - everyone remembers just the bits that hit it out of the park.  Still, there&amp;rsquo;s an undeniable relevation about leadership in this quote and I repeat it when mentoring young managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not what you preach, it&amp;rsquo;s what you tolerate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jocko Willink&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;on-gratitude&#34;&gt;On Gratitude&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finish with the subject that has most influenced my &amp;ldquo;mature&amp;rdquo; years.  I&amp;rsquo;ve worked to become a grateful person and to recognize that I&amp;rsquo;m blessed in myriad ways.  To list just three: I have a wonderful wife and amazing children, I have friends around the world who want nothing but good for me, and I have the opportunity to do meaningful work.  Focusing on those gifts has brought a peace and happiness to my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, I thought that Stoicism was depressing.  I&amp;rsquo;ve come to realize that it provides perfect perspective for a grateful life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing is more honorable than a grateful heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seneca&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and also&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is a wise man who does not grieve for the things which he has not, but rejoices for those which he has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epictetus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sincerely hope that - if you take nothing else - these thoughts on gratitude will resonate and be useful.  As a Christian, I&amp;rsquo;ll end with the most meaningful quote to me, taken from the end of the Sermon on the Mount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore do not worry about tomorrow, for tomorrow will worry about itself. Each day has enough trouble of its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark 6:34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
