<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About on Nextpertise</title>
    <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/tags/about/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About on Nextpertise</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 11:38:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.nextpertise.net/tags/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About Nextpertise</title>
      <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 11:38:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nextpertise.net/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This website is a place where we can write about and share the things we&amp;rsquo;re working on.  Our interests are varied, so the content will range a bit.  Your respectful thoughts and suggestions are welcomed.  Articles will be updated as better ideas emerge!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help you make the most of the site, the articles are tagged in a way that lets you filter to the posts you need.  Some articles will have a youtube reference; this will point to a youtube channel where a video version of the article is available.  Some articles have a github reference.  As much as possible, we will create a repository of each project so that you can clone and improve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we&amp;rsquo;ve learned these things through the works of others.  Where possible, attributions or additional references for further reading have been included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wish you the best on your journey!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-brent-stewart&#34;&gt;About Brent Stewart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been in the IT industry for about 30 years.  Early in my career, I benefitted enormously from a knowledgeable mentor.  I&amp;rsquo;ve found that my default approach to a lot of my career has been to teach, whether I&amp;rsquo;m part of a team, leadership, working with clients, or explaining things to management.  I hope that I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to mentor others along the way and &amp;ldquo;pay it forward.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s in Physics and a Masters in Computer Science / Information Security.  I&amp;rsquo;ve written numerous books, mostly for Cisco Press.  I&amp;rsquo;ve included links below to the ones still in print.  I&amp;rsquo;ve been employed as an IT Director and I&amp;rsquo;ve included my LinkedIn profile below - feel free to link to me and please mention that you saw my website!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My professional interests include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Networking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtualization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automation and Cloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My PCs all run Linux (mostly Ubuntu variants) and I work with and contribute to GNS3, so those topics will come up on this site.  On a personal note, I&amp;rsquo;ve been married 24 years and have four kids!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
