<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tiling on </title>
    <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/tags/tiling/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tiling on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2020 10:17:03 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.nextpertise.net/tags/tiling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Pop! OS</title>
      <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/201126_pop-os/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2020 10:17:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/201126_pop-os/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote about my experiences with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/ubuntu2010&#34;&gt;Ubuntu 20.10&lt;/a&gt;.  In that article, I mentioned that I previously found Gnome laggy and the app picker to be annoyingly unsorted.  That article got into Gnome 3.38, which seems to answer my issues by being perkier and providing a way to organize applications.  I also mentioend how much I appreciated Material Design, a tiling extension for Gnome.  That setup - Ubuntu 20.10 with Gnome 3.38 and Material Design - has worked really well on my laptop and a month later I remain enthusiastic about the way it organizes my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pop.system76.com/_nuxt/img/623f266-700.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Pop OS&#34;&gt;
But . . . it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work so well on my desktop setup.  The desktop is an i7 with 64GB of memory (perfect for GNS3!) and a 2K and 4K display.  The Material Design extension didn&amp;rsquo;t adapt well to the dual displays.  Gnome was still great, so I started hunting for a different tiling extension but the others didn&amp;rsquo;t install on 3.38.  I had tried &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; six months ago and really liked where System 76 was headed with auto-tiling, but had been frustrated by Gnome.  I decided to give the distribution another chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; is an opinionated re-distribution of stock (Gnome) Ubuntu.  System 76 is a long time manufacturer of Linux computers.  They have a great reputation in the community and have been a big promoter and sponsor within the community.  A couple years ago, they decided to customize Ubuntu to optimize the experience for their hardware.  They labeled the result &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; and made it available for anyone to use.  &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; 20.10 came out shortly after Ubuntu 20.10 in seperate releases for computers with NVidia cards and those with AMD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious differnce between stock Ubuntu and &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; is the Gnome setup and skin.  Ubuntu has a very specific user experience and they have their own take on Gnome.  This isn&amp;rsquo;t a criticism.  System 76 has built a different experience, with a more &amp;ldquo;standard&amp;rdquo; Gnome setup but with their Auto-tiling extension.  There is also a relentlessly upbeat feel to the skinning and backgrounds.  It&amp;rsquo;s a peppiness that belies how darn useful the OS is.  Ubuntu is also moving very heavily toward snaps and &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; supports snaps but is built more along &lt;strong&gt;apt&lt;/strong&gt; lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience is that 20.10 improves on 19.10, as one would expect.  The lagginess I saw before is now gone, which may be attributable to updated Gnome desktop.  All the things that I loved about Auto-Tiling are still present, they just work better.  On big displays, I really don&amp;rsquo;t see why you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want this experience.  Opening a new window automatically divides the display either vertically or horizontally.  Gnome supports multiple workspaces, and I have been setting up desktops for specific workflows (like one for blogging that I&amp;rsquo;m using now).  I don&amp;rsquo;t like the workspace switcher that ships with &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt;, so I installed Workspace Matrix.  I also added &lt;em&gt;Dash to Dock&lt;/em&gt; to give a dock and put the application button in a better location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first experimented with Tiling using i3 and later Regolith.  Regolith in particular has a lot going for it and really opened my eyes to the possibilities, but I found both to be a lot of trouble to setup and work inside.  i3 is very keyboard heavy and the folks who enjoy it the most are very keyboard oriented.  &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; provides a similar experience, but it&amp;rsquo;s less laborious in a number of ways.  Tiling happens automatically, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t like the arrangement you can drag windows around to adjust the tiling.  It&amp;rsquo;s easier to setup exceptions (pop-up windows, like my password database, that should float and not re-tile the screen).  Keyboard shortcuts are supported, if you are oriented that way, but I rarely have used them in my testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; also has a conventional Gnome app picker.  Here I have a quibble - I would still prefer a heirarchical menu.  If anyone can suggest a good &lt;em&gt;Dash to Dock&lt;/em&gt; or Gnome extension in the comments, I&amp;rsquo;d appreciate it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/Peek_Pop!_OS.webp#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Brent playing with Tiling&#34;&gt;
The animated GIF here is me playing around.  I have two displays - a horizontal 4k on the right and a vertical 2k on the left.  There&amp;rsquo;s a gray area above the 4k because of the way the resolutions match up.  You can see Tilix and GNS3 open on the 4k, and Wireshark and an additional Tilix window open and automatically Tile.  Then I open the application picker on and fonts on the other display.  You can see &lt;em&gt;Dash to Dock&lt;/em&gt; and get a sense of how the system works.  You can also see that Gnome 3.38 now supports grouping applications, like Android, which I find a big improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other differences besides tiling between &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; and Ubuntu.  There are different application &amp;ldquo;stores&amp;rdquo; and update interfaces, but both accomplish the same things in similar ways.  There are different packaged apps, but you can install anything you need from PPA or snap on either system so this doesn&amp;rsquo;t strike me as worth cataloging.  I used my standard Ubuntu post-install script when I setup &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; and everything worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why not just install the &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; extension on Ubuntu?  Well, it can be done.  System 76 publishes it to their Github.  They&amp;rsquo;ve packaged it for Fedora, but not yet for Ubuntu, so it would have to be built.  That&amp;rsquo;s not a mountain to climb, but I was ready for a clean install anyway and opted for the full &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t say how much I appreciate what System 76 has done.  They&amp;rsquo;ve created a slightly different take on Ubuntu that looks great on their hardware and they&amp;rsquo;ve made all the parts - from a full OS install to the &amp;ldquo;secret sauce&amp;rdquo; extension easily accessible to the community.  I find &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; enjoyable and useful and plan on keeping it installed on this machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My laptop is running fine using Ubuntu 20.10 with the Material Design extension, and there&amp;rsquo;s not enough of a difference to make me re-install it.   Besides, I&amp;rsquo;d like to see where each tiler goes.  There&amp;rsquo;s a lot in Material Design to recommend it and it&amp;rsquo;s still early days for that extension.  Frankly, &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite baked at that stage either.  I intend to keep &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; on the Desktop. The current &lt;em&gt;Pop! OS&lt;/em&gt; 20.10 feels sharp, responsive, and really well done and I look forward to seeing where System 76 takes this idea next.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tilix</title>
      <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/201125_tilix/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 07:50:59 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/201125_tilix/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gnunn1.github.io/tilix-web/src/images/gallery/tilix-screenshot-3.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Tilix&#34;&gt; Tilix is a terminal application for Linux that I recommend as a replacement for the stock program (like gnome-terminal) shipped with your distribution.  This article will walk through some of the reasons I like Tilix and will show you how to use it with GNS3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic pitch of Tilix is that it is a tiling terminal.  New terminals exist in sessions.  Within a session, terminals can split the window horizontally or veritcally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a session like a desktop.  You could create a poor-man&amp;rsquo;s IDE by grouping three sessions on a desktop, with one showing a directory, a second running &lt;strong&gt;nano&lt;/strong&gt;, and the third ready to receive a command.  Another session could be used for networking, with terminals open to a firewall and switch.  You manage sessions with the drop-down menu on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sessions can be divided up into terminals.  New terminals split the screen.  You create a new terminal using the &amp;ldquo;horizontal split&amp;rdquo; button or the &amp;ldquo;vertical split&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of additional features, such as a search function (particularly useful when scrolling through thousands of lines of syslog output), but the tiling features are what makes this program so darn useful to me.  As I have moved to larger displays (I typically work on a 40&amp;quot; 4K display these days), managing windows is more of a chore and I prefer things that help organize the desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://camo.githubusercontent.com/b0862287feb56d682f22cfa67bc43f5cfa2fd5b59fc291533be741015c6766af/68747470733a2f2f7261772e6769746875622e636f6d2f622d7279616e2f706f7765726c696e652d7368656c6c2f6d61737465722f626173682d706f7765726c696e652d73637265656e73686f742e706e67#floatleft&#34; alt=&#34;Powerline&#34;&gt;Tilix supports any customization that a normal terminal application allows.  I&amp;rsquo;ll dig a little into this aspect in a seperate article, but I&amp;rsquo;ve included links for some of the ways I make my terminal easy to read.  I use the &lt;strong&gt;powerline-shell&lt;/strong&gt; prompt.  I use either JetBrains Mono font or Fira Mono, which both support programming ligatures.  There&amp;rsquo;s a variety of other monospace fonts with ligature support at the Powerline Git Repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-tilix-with-gns3&#34;&gt;Using Tilix with GNS3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/Tilix_in_GNS3.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Tilix with GNS3&#34;&gt;
GNS3 allows you to set the terminal application it uses under &lt;em&gt;edit &amp;gt; preferences&lt;/em&gt;.  The drop-down for console sets GNS3 to work with some of the most common applications, such as &lt;em&gt;gnome-terminal&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;PuTTY&lt;/em&gt;.  Tilix isn&amp;rsquo;t defined, but it works &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; well in this scenario because GNS3 users typically have several terminal sessions on-going and need to easily move between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To configure GNS3 to work with Tilix, choose &amp;ldquo;custom&amp;rdquo; and &lt;strong&gt;edit&lt;/strong&gt;.  Here&amp;rsquo;s the command that is needed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;tilix -a session-add-right -t &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;%d&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; -e &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;telnet %h %p&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This setup uses Tilix and opens new terminals to the right of the existing one.  Other options set the title and tell Tilix how to connect to the GNS3 device.  The variables are defined in GNS3 and are visible in the &lt;strong&gt;edit&lt;/strong&gt; screen - %d is the tile, %h is the IP and %p is the port. Tilix has a man page if you want to investigate other options.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ubuntu 20.10</title>
      <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/201024_ubuntu2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 18:40:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/201024_ubuntu2010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had a chance to download Ubuntu 20.10 and install it on a gen 8 i5 laptop.  I typically use Cinnamon for a desktop environment, which I have long found to be mature, usable, and stable.  In the past, I&amp;rsquo;ve found Gnome to be laggy but I&amp;rsquo;ve heard good things about 3.38.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve become enamored of tiling windows as well.  I&amp;rsquo;ve tried i3, Pop OS!, and others.  So another thing I wanted to look into was the Material Design extension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-ubuntu-2010&#34;&gt;About Ubuntu 20.10&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu releases a Long Term Support (LTS) release biannually.  LTS versions, like 20.04,  are supported for five years and are appropriate for business servers.  Interim releases like 20.10 are supported for nine months.  These releases are kept current and represent the most up-to-date implementation of Ubuntu&amp;rsquo;s vision for the Linux desktop.  Ubuntu supports a variety of DEs including KDE, Budgie, MATE and others. There are unsupported versions for Cinnamon and Deepin as well.  I&amp;rsquo;ve used the MATE version for VMs in the past and it&amp;rsquo;s performed very well, but this time I wanted to check out Gnome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two things that jumped out at me have to do with login.  First, there&amp;rsquo;s now a built in choice to authenticate via Active Directory.  I have several workstations and servers and the idea of being able to easily centralize authentication is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; appealing.  I haven&amp;rsquo;t had time to build that part out, but I will be looking into that process in the months ahead.  I&amp;rsquo;m hoping I can make it work with FreeIPA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing - and this sounds minor - is the responsiveness of the login screen.  It&amp;rsquo;s been my past opinion that Gnome was slow, but logging in is breezy.  I use Windows 10 at work and the Ubuntu lock screen is especially quick comparted to that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default Gnome experience has an &lt;em&gt;application grid&lt;/em&gt; like Android (all the apps in alphabetical order).  This was always annoying to me - partly because I&amp;rsquo;m a heirarchical organizer and partly because I could never remember the name of the app I wanted.  The new 3.38 allows you to organize your apps in whatever order makes sense to you and to pull icons into folders.  This is a big win for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu is still running Gnome on X.  X Windows is stable and mature and has better support for NVidia video cards, but the next generation Wayland is coming and Ubuntu hasn&amp;rsquo;t pushed that envelope yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu 20.10 includes Linux kernel 5.8.0.25.  This was billed as the &amp;ldquo;biggest release of all time&amp;rdquo; by Linux Torvalds.  Most of the improvements are around drivers and the Spectre patch.  According to Phoronix, there&amp;rsquo;s good benefit for ATI graphics.  Otherwise, from a desktop perspective, this won&amp;rsquo;t be a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications, such as LibreOffice (7.0), Firefox (82), and Thunderbird (78.3.2), have been updated to latest versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the biggest difference between Gnome and Mate or Cinnamon is app selection.  At the end of the day, despite the improved performance, it&amp;rsquo;s not enough to make me want to switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tiling-with-material-design&#34;&gt;Tiling with Material Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned before, the window tiling paradigm really makes sense to me.  I&amp;rsquo;ve tried i3 and Regolith, which I like, but they suffer from the same problem as Gnome - having an easy way to browse available applications.  Pop OS! has a tiling extension for Gnome that&amp;rsquo;s well thought out, but I abandoned it because it made Gnome &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; responsive.  Still, the Pop OS! experience came the closest to what I imagined tiling could be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I was introduced to &lt;strong&gt;Material Design&lt;/strong&gt;.  I decided to install it on my new Ubuntu 20.10 installation and try to &amp;ldquo;live in it&amp;rdquo; for a better test.  &lt;strong&gt;Material Design&lt;/strong&gt; is a gnome extension that provides a few really specific tiling options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install Material Design in Ubuntu 20.10, go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://extensions.gnome.org&#34;&gt;https://extensions.gnome.org&lt;/a&gt; and add the extension.  Unfortunately, Ubuntu doesn&amp;rsquo;t support the Gnome add-in page out of the box.  At the Gnome page, load the firefox extension.  You&amp;rsquo;ll also need to install some supporting pieces for it to run properly.  Note that the chrome-gnome-shell is used by both Firefox and Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;sudo apt-get install libproxy1-plugin-networkmanager gnome-shell-extension-system-monitor  
sudo apt-get install chrome-gnome-shell  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows are on desktops, with the taskbar across the top showing you what&amp;rsquo;s on the current desktop.  Desktops are shown on the side bar, so you can think of the two bars as showing a grid of apps X desktops. The version of Material design at Gnome supports four windowing modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single Window - each application takes up the full window and you can use the taskbar to move easily between them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Split - each application takes up either the left or right half of the screen.  The app order is shown on the taskbar, and you can drag to rearrange.  Many times I&amp;rsquo;m typing in one window with another for reference, so this mode sets up exactly what I&amp;rsquo;m looking for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Half - the first application occupies the left half of the screen.  Subsequent apps stack to the right.  You can drag windows or rearrange the taskbar to change which applications go in each spot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free - this is the &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; Gnome experience, with tiling turned off.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/material-shell/material-shell/master/documentation/tiling_showcase.gif#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Material Design&#34;&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my testing, I found that I could set different modes for each desktop.  Right now, the desktop I&amp;rsquo;m typing on has Codium on one side and a browser on the other in &amp;ldquo;Split&amp;rdquo; mode.  My other desktop use &amp;ldquo;Half&amp;rdquo; with a big browser on the right and a terminal, Enpass, and settings stacked on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also installed the &lt;strong&gt;Gnome menu&lt;/strong&gt; so that I&amp;rsquo;d have the heirarchical app picking experience I like.  Material shell has a button for the gnome app grid but I want something different.  I&amp;rsquo;m unimpressed with &lt;strong&gt;Gnome Menu&lt;/strong&gt;.  Anyone want to recommend a menu extension?  Gnome Menu hits the minimum reqs - it&amp;rsquo;s an organized menu.  On the other hand, you can&amp;rsquo;t type to search, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t open sub-menus automatically, and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t a place where frequently used apps or files can be quickly found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end though, the beauty of Linux is that the machine is &lt;em&gt;yours&lt;/em&gt;.  In a half hour I installed a new distro with a new DE, updated it and installed some critical apps, customized the desktop for tiling and changed the application selection process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep Ubuntu 20.10 and Material Design on this machine for a while.  It works well on the 1920x1080 17&amp;quot; display.  I&amp;rsquo;m also curious how the combination will work on my desktop with it&amp;rsquo;s two 4k displays, but I&amp;rsquo;ll take a little time before making that decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu 20.10 has answered my objections to the laggy experience of Gnome and given me a &amp;ldquo;standard&amp;rdquo; desktop experience I can customize to my interests.  I&amp;rsquo;m curious about your impressions - write to me and let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
