<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Non-Technical on </title>
    <link>https://nextpertise.net/tags/non-technical/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Non-Technical on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 15:58:38 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://nextpertise.net/tags/non-technical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>AI-Pocolypse Now</title>
      <link>https://nextpertise.net/posts/230805_ai-pocolypse_now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 15:58:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nextpertise.net/posts/230805_ai-pocolypse_now/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My friends know that I am an avid reader and that I love Science Fiction.  I&amp;rsquo;ve read that Science Fiction only became possible when people could see technology changing in their lifetime, and although we had slow changes for a long time it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until the last half of the 19th Century that we got &lt;em&gt;Frankenstein&lt;/em&gt;.  Even in Mary Shelley&amp;rsquo;s time, though, the pace of change was slow compared to now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a fascinating time to live!  I was born five days after Neil Armstrong set foot on the moon.  Communication - including the Internet - has completely revolutionized the way we relate to others and ourselves several times in my life (fax machines, cell phones, SMS, e-mail, social media).  Cancer used to be a get-your-affairs-in-order conversation.  It&amp;rsquo;s still not good, but the progress from when my uncle Paul died in the 70s until now is &lt;em&gt;astounding&lt;/em&gt;.  Logistics has changed the world - strawberries from South America in the dead of winter?  Having seen all these things, it can feel like my life has been science fiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to the AI-pocolypse, my campy-and-probably-not-original name for the fear that our technological creations will supplant us.  Funny aside, but that&amp;rsquo;s what Frankenstein was about as well.  Science Fiction has a way of predicting the future - it&amp;rsquo;s like a dream half remembered that reveals something about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-first-four-signs&#34;&gt;The first four signs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the genre.  What are the classical elements of machines gone mad and taking over?  My offhand list would be access to an incredible amount of knowledge, insight into people - even into &amp;ldquo;private&amp;rdquo; and personal thoughts, a capability to plan and act, an opportunity that carbon-able people create because we want something from the machines, and evil intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, check, check, check, check, and . . . not necessary?  I&amp;rsquo;m going to argue that the AI-pocolypse is already upon us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Science Fiction, the first thing the &amp;ldquo;robots&amp;rdquo; need to take  over is all the knowledge.  Wow, the web really made this easy and fun to do.  Computers have all our writing, all the papers, all the facts we know.  Advances like Machine Learning and even ChatGPT demonstrates that there are ways to use all that knowledge to start to draw inferences and power new advances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second thing the computers need is insight into our personal thoughts so that they can draw inferences, anticipate behavior, manipulate us or out-think us.  Too late.  This has been a reality for about a decade. Computers have been used to learn our patterns and manipulate us so that we are a necessary step in their food cycle.  Manipulate Brent into clicking on an ad, ad generates revenue, the profit from which buys electricty to feed the machine.  Each of us, like docile cattle, seeks out the supercomputer and aims it squarely at our brains.  Examples include Facebook, Cambridge Analytica (also Facebook), Google, Twitter, Reddit, and pretty much the whole Internet.  Like the old adage goes, if they&amp;rsquo;re not charging you then you are the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are starting to feel uncomfortable, think about the ability of computers to plan and act.  Things like chatbots show an ability to plan at an abstract level.  Yes, I know that these are language models that are drawing on human sources and generating a response that is statistically likely to meet your expectations, but if you ask them something like &amp;ldquo;how do I change the oil in my car?&amp;rdquo; they will give you a series of steps.  Even more to my point, consider Space-X Falcon rockets and their ability to understand thrust and wind and land on their tailfans.  Or the Boston Dynamics robot dogs, that can be given tasks like patrolling a perimeter or inspecting a dangerous site.  Computers are now routinely interacting with the physical world (see &amp;ldquo;Internet of Things&amp;rdquo;) and taking actions, actions that are necessary and consistent to acheive an outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three for three.  Number four on my list was opportunity.  In the classic plot, the AI rises to power through lazy humans.  Examples include Skynet (built to protect lazy humans), AUTO (from Wall-E, built to serve lazy consumers), and HAL (built to keep a secret because it couldn&amp;rsquo;t be trusted to other humans).  So, take a deep breath and look around and ask yourself if there are opportunities.  Would one side in a war pause if an AI could help win it?   The answer is no.  Are we too lazy to drive to a store to shop now?  The answer is yes.  How much do you depend on Google Maps?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;evil-intent&#34;&gt;Evil Intent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my daughter asked me a while back if I believed people were basically good or bad.  Neither, I replied, I believe that they are basically selfish.  When one of the boys asked if he was selfish, I told him that I was.  An ability to put others needs above our own is an aspirational point for religion.  The Recognition that others perspectives are valid is a high point of philosphy (Kant&amp;rsquo;s Categorical Imperative).  So let&amp;rsquo;s start with the idea that selfish is easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evil is complicated.  Selfish is taking the last cookie.  Evil is intentionally starving someone, or even taking actions designed to inflict pain for personal enjoyment.  Evil does exist, no question.  Thankfully, in my experience, evil is rare and an exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purpose of thinking about the AI-pocolypse, whatever that is, I&amp;rsquo;m going to argue that evil is unnecessary.  I have two reasons for saying this: first, evil is complicated and selfish is simple and programmers like simple.  Second, a person can die of starvation because someone else is hoarding food.  The hoarder may see themselves as good, after all they are protecting their family, not enjoying the suffering of others.  But dead is dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selfishness isn&amp;rsquo;t even a bad thing.  Acting selfishly impels us to preserve ourselves.  Any being that doesn&amp;rsquo;t see their existence as having value would be suicidal.  Can computers be selfish?  We can argue, but computers can certainly carry out a set of selfish actions designed to maximize gain accrued to their owner.  For example, there are high-frequency trading platforms that algorithmically pursue profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if the computers can outsource selfishness?  What if that part doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be a part of their program.  An algorithm, whatever level of sentience you claim for it, still works through instructions that we give it.  If the people that are building it and directing it are selfish, does the AI need to have that as a feature?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it&amp;rsquo;s an algorithm or a Billionaire, does it matter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;and&#34;&gt;And?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we agree, what do we do about it?  I&amp;rsquo;m not sure, so I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about what I intend to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step is to recognize the situation.  The environment is created by tecnology and empowered by our laziness.  I&amp;rsquo;m not going to become some new kind of Amish, trying to trap the 1980s in amber, nor do I believe that anyone would go along with me if I proposed it.  The part that is under my control is my laziness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So action #1 is to become digitally self-soverign, at least to the extent that I can.  That means understanding the technology and not oursourcing my data to the &amp;ldquo;cloud&amp;rdquo; (cloud is just a fancy word for a Billionaire&amp;rsquo;s computer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action #2 is to hide and lie.  Computers are able to assemble a lot of seemingly random things and use them to identify a person.  Companies may ask for random pieces of data, like a hometown or birthday, and then pair that with the mountain of data that exists on the Internet to target me.  So I intend to encrypt my data at rest and in transit, to obfuscate my tracks, and to use random data when interacting with non-official records collection.  Good examples of these ideas are to use private VPN, to trade affinity cards with others to confuse the analysis (these are the bar code cards that stores give you), and to use a password manager to store your made-up details for each company you deal with (changing things like birthday, location, and even favorite color).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action #3 is to study moral philoophy and my religion, and to encourage those around me to do the same.  Right and wrong can&amp;rsquo;t simply be words we use to justify selfish decisions.  My experience is that the vast majority of folks are not evil but are very selfish.  Selfishness is our natural &amp;ldquo;resting state&amp;rdquo;.  Overcoming this selfishness requires continuous effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve personally benefitted from a number of approaches to overcoming selfishness.  First is marriage and parenthood.  Making space in your life for others, making them more important than yourself, and listening to the feedback they give you is a huge gift when it comes to recognizing your own weakness and trying to be a better person.  Second, I&amp;rsquo;ve found friends who I agree with sometimes and friends from whom  I can learn.  I have friends from other faith-traditions, from other political persuasions, and who just enjoy different things.  Again, choosing to care for other people and finding people who care about you helps me recognize that I have the capacity to be wrong or to choose what is expeditious over what is good.  Reading is also a great way to grow yourself.  I publish a list of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stewart.tc/reading/&#34;&gt;books I&amp;rsquo;ve read&lt;/a&gt; if you are interested.  It&amp;rsquo;s important to understand that reading is not a solitary activity - it only gets incorporated, at least for me, when you share it with people you respect, think about it together, and make it your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like I&amp;rsquo;ve lately benefitted a lot from reading about Stoicism  and so I try to care for truth and I choose to be thankful and find joy. I wish nothing less than that for each of you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IMHO</title>
      <link>https://nextpertise.net/posts/230122_announcing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 13:27:41 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nextpertise.net/posts/230122_announcing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve created a seperate site - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stewart.tc&#34;&gt;Stewart.tc&lt;/a&gt; - to house my book reviews, discoveries, and thoughts on non-Internet subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I titled this &amp;ldquo;IMHO&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;in my humble opinion&amp;rdquo;, but I&amp;rsquo;ve always tried to avoid opinions in this space on non-technical topics.  Even the &amp;ldquo;non-technical&amp;rdquo; tag is about Internet topics for presentation to non-techies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started writing because I enjoy sharing what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned and because I enjoy writing and wanted to develop the skill by making it more of a discipline.  Writing helps to organize thoughts and get them out of your head.  The idea that I can pursue IT ideas that fascinate me and share those findings with others has been great, and along the way I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered that I refer back to my own writing fairly often to remember how to do &lt;em&gt;that thing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve grown and my circumstances have evolved, I&amp;rsquo;ve had less time to pursue IT ideas but more time to think on other topics.  I tried to include some of that here, for instance in the book reviews, but in the end felt that it was best persued in a seperate forum.  So, if you have enjoyed my book notes or are interested in my thoughts on deconstructionism, I invite you to check out the new site.  I moved the book reviews over to that site, but there&amp;rsquo;s not much else there so far so you may want to check back in a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site will continue, probably at about the same pace, and I hope that it will continue to occassionally offer something of use to you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DNS Services</title>
      <link>https://nextpertise.net/posts/200826_dnsservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 12:01:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nextpertise.net/posts/200826_dnsservices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is to continue the conversation started in &lt;a href=&#34;https://nextpertise.net/posts/200805_reasonablysecurebrowsing&#34;&gt;Reasonably Secure Browsing&lt;/a&gt; with some options for home DNS setting that help protect you and your family.  Like that post, this is intended for non-industry friends.  My goal is to have a set of references for the people I care about, but who don&amp;rsquo;t share my love of technology.  For the gurus out there, understand that this leaves out a lot of details for the sake of clarity for the target audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first post covered browser settings that balanced security, privacy concerns, and convenience.  Another way to improve your security is use an alternative DNS provider.  DNS (Domain Name System) is an under-the-hood service that connects a name like &amp;ldquo;amazon.com&amp;rdquo; with a number like 176.32.103.205.  Think about your mobile phone.  We rarely memorize peoples telephone numbers anymore, we just call &amp;ldquo;Brent&amp;rdquo; or choose the picture that matches the person we want to call.  The phone translates that into a telephone number.  DNS is a centralized process that translates a name to a number to make the internet more &amp;ldquo;human friendly&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should you care?  Three reasons - speed, security, and privacy.  DNS is typically set up by your Internet provider.  Sometimes these implementations are the sources of problems, so changing the default DNS will give you a more stable (and sometimes faster) experience.  Anyone &amp;ldquo;listening&amp;rdquo; to your traffic can easily make a list of where you visit by tracking DNS requests.  This could be someone snooping on a shared wifi at the coffee shop, or it could be your ISP (in fact, ISPs sometimes redirect your traffic to internet locations they control for their own benefit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a set of alternative DNS providers that provide free services that are unfiltered and private.  I recommend that you consider one of these.  They&amp;rsquo;re all good, but I&amp;rsquo;ve listed them in the order of my preference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enable, go into your router and change the DNS setting to the IP provided (the exact instructions vary by router).  At home, this is a reasonable step to protect you and your family.  If you travel, these providers also support a variety of options to encrypt your request, including DNS over HTTPS (DoH).  I recommend using DoH within Firefox for devices that leave the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firefox can encrypt your DNS traffic from &amp;ldquo;snoopers&amp;rdquo;.  Go to the menu button and choose &lt;em&gt;preferences&lt;/em&gt; and then &lt;em&gt;Network Settings&lt;/em&gt;.  Click &lt;em&gt;Enable DNS over HTTPS&lt;/em&gt; and then choose a provider or select &amp;ldquo;Custom&amp;rdquo; and type in the IP address (included below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://d15ni2z53ptwz9.cloudfront.net/opendns-www/img/logo-opendns.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;OpenDNS&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;opendns-20867222222---best-for-home-use&#34;&gt;OpenDNS (208.67.222.222) - Best for home use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenDNS is a great choice.  By default, their free service is excellent.  It recognizes many cases where you&amp;rsquo;ve been directed to a malicious site, and keeps you out of trouble by blocking it.  OpenDNS is owned by Cisco, and it benefits from the huge investments they&amp;rsquo;ve made in Internet security.  It also blocks adult content by default.  You can create an account and customize your home&amp;rsquo;s experience - for instance, do you want to block Gambling or Tobacco advertising?  These settings are tied to your home IP, so your laptop goes back to the &amp;ldquo;default&amp;rdquo; when not at home.  Especially for public places, like church wifi, or for a home with children this allows you to control what portion of the Internet is available to users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cloudflare-unfiltered-1111-malware-blocking-1112-malware-and-adult-content-1113&#34;&gt;Cloudflare (unfiltered 1.1.1.1, malware blocking 1.1.1.2, malware and adult content 1.1.1.3)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloudflare is very easy to setup.  Use the IP address that matches your use case.  These settings can carry over when you are away from home if you change them on your device.  There&amp;rsquo;s also an app that provides this service no matter where you are (just for mobile with Windows and Mac coming soon).  Cloudflare has good settings for most cases, is easy to setup, and has the mobile apps, but lacks the customization of OpenDNS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;quad9-9999&#34;&gt;Quad9 (9.9.9.9)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quad9 provides a service that is very similar to Cloudflare 1.1.1.2 - just set the DNS and forget it and it provides DNS with malicious sites blocked.  My experience with Quad9 has been largely indistinguishable from Cloudflare or OpenDNS with default settings, when testing blocking or response speed.  However, Quad9 doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the customization of OpenDNS or the apps that Cloudflare has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;google-8888&#34;&gt;Google (8.8.8.8)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a popular alternative for the geek set for a long time.  It&amp;rsquo;s easy to remember and it provides an &amp;ldquo;unfiltered&amp;rdquo; response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using one of these services helps to protect your home.  I use OpenDNS at home and have customized it to filter out a range of categories.  It doesn&amp;rsquo;t block everything on the Internet, but it addresses some of the obvious sites and it helps prevent &amp;ldquo;oops&amp;rdquo; experiences.  It seems to help with advertising too.  I use Cloudflare on my office network and it does a great job as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve benefitted from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://nextpertise.net/posts/200805_reasonablysecurebrowsing&#34;&gt;Reasonably Secure Browsing&lt;/a&gt; discussion, this is another &amp;ldquo;reasonable&amp;rdquo; step that you can take to improve your families Internet experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reasonably Secure Browsing</title>
      <link>https://nextpertise.net/posts/200805_reasonablysecurebrowsing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 11:23:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nextpertise.net/posts/200805_reasonablysecurebrowsing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most of my articles are aimed at helping me remember how I did something &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt; years later, and helping other people who share my interest and want to solve similar problems.  This one is a little different.  When I speak to non-technical folks - at church, other parents, or within my family - I&amp;rsquo;m disappointed with the lack of understanding about computer security.  I was going to say &amp;ldquo;surprised&amp;rdquo;, but sadly I&amp;rsquo;m not.  This article tries to fix that by introducing this audience to concepts in Secure Browsing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get that we can&amp;rsquo;t all be aware of &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt;.  For instance, I&amp;rsquo;m not really interested in cars.  Still, if you are participating in an area (driving a car or browsing the web), then there&amp;rsquo;s a basic level of awareness that is needed and that you should aim for.  So this post is written for the non-technical in order to provide that grounding.  I&amp;rsquo;ll try to keep this up to date (pay attention to the posting date!) and I&amp;rsquo;ll start pointing people who ask those questions to this resource.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/0/09/Timmcgee.jpg#floatleft&#34; alt=&#34;Tim McGee from NCIS&#34;&gt;
I need to define &amp;ldquo;reasonable&amp;rdquo; before I get started.  Internet paranoia comes in three flavors - fear of malicious actors, fear of giant companies assembling dossiers to feed into marketing, and Orwellian fears about nation-states.  All three are reasonable things to be concerned about but this post only addresses the first.  Hiding from the NSA is beyond the ability of most people - even if they unplug.  Hiding from creepy companies is possible, but requires foregoing a lot of services that most of us are loathe to do without.  However, there are small steps that you can take that will give you a good degree of protection against maliciousness.  Reasonable means simple steps picking up bad code or leaking sensitive personal information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, what makes me think I&amp;rsquo;m an expert?  Well, I have a Master&amp;rsquo;s in Information Security and I&amp;rsquo;ve worked in IT operations and security for many, many years.  I&amp;rsquo;m no Tim McGee, but I get by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-safe-browsing-advice&#34;&gt;General safe-browsing advice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;If possible, run Linux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup your home to use OpenDNS or CloudFlare Family DNS servers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check for browser updates regularly, and apply them.  Keep plugins up to date as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Anti-Virus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t &lt;strong&gt;ever&lt;/strong&gt; click on links in email.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a secure password, and don’t re-use passwords between sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not save passwords within the browser. Use a password safe and subscribe to &lt;strong&gt;Have I been Pwned?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use SSL – Sites that use “HTTPS:” instead of “HTTP” are encrypting your traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a solution to monitor your bank accounts and credit reports.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-browser-checklist&#34;&gt;General Browser checklist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not save passwords in the browser.  Use a password safe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not use autofill.  Sites use hidden fields to send more than you think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have the browser ask you where to save files.  This alerts you to files being downloaded and allows you to cancel or put them in a folder for latter consideration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable click-to-play for plugins.  This will speed up the browser and allow you to decide when to use useful but potentially dangerous plugins like JavaScript, Flash, and Silverlight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not accept third-party cookies except by exception.  Clear all cookies after each session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Do Not Track.  This is more aimed at commercial privacy, and depends on the server honoring the request, but why not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be cautious using extensions, however there are a few that are suggested:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AdBlock Plus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTTPS Everywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refer to the following sections for specific help with your browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;chromehttpswwwmozillaorgmediaprotocolimglogosfirefoxbrowserlogo-lg-high-resfbc7ffbb50fdpngfloatright-chrome&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.mozilla.org/media/protocol/img/logos/firefox/browser/logo-lg-high-res.fbc7ffbb50fd.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Chrome&#34;&gt; Chrome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settings are found under the “stacked dots” icon on the right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under “set up sync”
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose “encrypt all synced data with your sync password”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uncheck Autofill and Passwords.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select advanced options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Privacy, check “protect you and your device from dangerous sites” and “send Do Not Track”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Passwords and Forms, uncheck both options (do not autofill or remember passwords).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Downloads, check “Ask where to save each file before downloading”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Plugins, select “Let me choose when to run plugin content”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Cookies, block third-party cookies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add recommended Extensions and remove un-needed ones.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AdBlock Plus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTTPS Everywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;firefoxhttpsp1hiclipartcompreview4981015635mozilla-sleek-icons-firefox-256x256-mozilla-firefox-logo-png-clipartjpgfloatright-firefox&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://p1.hiclipart.com/preview/498/1015/635/mozilla-sleek-icons-firefox-256x256-mozilla-firefox-logo-png-clipart.jpg#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Firefox&#34;&gt; Firefox&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Options are found under the “hamburger” icon on the right.  In the drop down menu, select preferences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;em&gt;Files and Applications&lt;/em&gt; and select “Always ask me where to save files.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under &lt;em&gt;Network Settings&lt;/em&gt; select the settings button.  Choose &lt;strong&gt;enable DNS over HTTPS&lt;/strong&gt; and set it to Cloudflare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under &lt;em&gt;Privacy &amp;amp; Security&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the Standard Tracking Protection option and “Always apply Do Not Track”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set third-party cookies to delete when Firefox is closed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Logins and Passwods, disable &amp;ldquo;ask to save&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Forms and Autofill, disable Autofill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Permissions, check &amp;ldquo;Warn me when sites try to install an add-on&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Block pop-up windows&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disable Firefox data collection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Security, choose to Block dangerous and deceptive content, block dangerous downloads, and warn about unwanted software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back to the hamburger menu and select &lt;em&gt;Add Ons&lt;/em&gt;.  Remove any extensions you don&amp;rsquo;t need and add these two.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AdBlock Plus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTTPS Everywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;internet-explorer&#34;&gt;Internet Explorer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t use Internet Explorer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-browsers---&#34;&gt;Other browsers . . .&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some other browsers that are marketed as &amp;ldquo;secure&amp;rdquo;.  Examples include Avast, AVG, and Comodo.  My experience is that these are just custom versions of Chrome.  It&amp;rsquo;s difficult to keep up with all the customizations these different groups make, but generally I find that they are based on an older version of Chromium and aren&amp;rsquo;t always transparent about what changes they are making.  They tend to be updated less often and sometimes behave in unexpected ways because of the changes.  I do not recommend these today, but I&amp;rsquo;m open to the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another set of browsers attempt to compete more directly with Firefox and Chrome.  These include names like Brave and Opera.  I have a good opinion of both these options, but they are more common with power users and not really in scope of this guide.  Safari is used on Macs and is quite good.  I&amp;rsquo;ll try to add it in at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
