<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Non-Technical on </title>
    <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/tags/non-technical/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Non-Technical on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 12:01:51 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.nextpertise.net/tags/non-technical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>DNS Services</title>
      <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/200826_dnsservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 12:01:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/200826_dnsservices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is to continue the conversation started in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/ReasonablySecureBrowsing&#34;&gt;Reasonably Secure Browsing&lt;/a&gt; with some options for home DNS setting that help protect you and your family.  Like that post, this is intended for non-industry friends.  My goal is to have a set of references for the people I care about, but who don&amp;rsquo;t share my love of technology.  For the gurus out there, understand that this leaves out a lot of details for the sake of clarity for the target audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first post covered browser settings that balanced security, privacy concerns, and convenience.  Another way to improve your security is use an alternative DNS provider.  DNS (Domain Name System) is an under-the-hood service that connects a name like &amp;ldquo;amazon.com&amp;rdquo; with a number like 176.32.103.205.  Think about your mobile phone.  We rarely memorize peoples telephone numbers anymore, we just call &amp;ldquo;Brent&amp;rdquo; or choose the picture that matches the person we want to call.  The phone translates that into a telephone number.  DNS is a centralized process that translates a name to a number to make the internet more &amp;ldquo;human friendly&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should you care?  Three reasons - speed, security, and privacy.  DNS is typically set up by your Internet provider.  Sometimes these implementations are the sources of problems, so changing the default DNS will give you a more stable (and sometimes faster) experience.  Anyone &amp;ldquo;listening&amp;rdquo; to your traffic can easily make a list of where you visit by tracking DNS requests.  This could be someone snooping on a shared wifi at the coffee shop, or it could be your ISP (in fact, ISPs sometimes redirect your traffic to internet locations they control for their own benefit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a set of alternative DNS providers that provide free services that are unfiltered and private.  I recommend that you consider one of these.  They&amp;rsquo;re all good, but I&amp;rsquo;ve listed them in the order of my preference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enable, go into your router and change the DNS setting to the IP provided (the exact instructions vary by router).  At home, this is a reasonable step to protect you and your family.  If you travel, these providers also support a variety of options to encrypt your request, including DNS over HTTPS (DoH).  I recommend using DoH within Firefox for devices that leave the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firefox can encrypt your DNS traffic from &amp;ldquo;snoopers&amp;rdquo;.  Go to the menu button and choose &lt;em&gt;preferences&lt;/em&gt; and then &lt;em&gt;Network Settings&lt;/em&gt;.  Click &lt;em&gt;Enable DNS over HTTPS&lt;/em&gt; and then choose a provider or select &amp;ldquo;Custom&amp;rdquo; and type in the IP address (included below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://d15ni2z53ptwz9.cloudfront.net/opendns-www/img/logo-opendns.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;OpenDNS&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;opendns-20867222222---best-for-home-use&#34;&gt;OpenDNS (208.67.222.222) - Best for home use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenDNS is a great choice.  By default, their free service is excellent.  It recognizes many cases where you&amp;rsquo;ve been directed to a malicious site, and keeps you out of trouble by blocking it.  OpenDNS is owned by Cisco, and it benefits from the huge investments they&amp;rsquo;ve made in Internet security.  It also blocks adult content by default.  You can create an account and customize your home&amp;rsquo;s experience - for instance, do you want to block Gambling or Tobacco advertising?  These settings are tied to your home IP, so your laptop goes back to the &amp;ldquo;default&amp;rdquo; when not at home.  Especially for public places, like church wifi, or for a home with children this allows you to control what portion of the Internet is available to users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cloudflare.com/#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;CloudFlare&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cloudflare-unfiltered-1111-malware-blocking-1112-malware-and-adult-content-1113---best-for-travelers&#34;&gt;Cloudflare (unfiltered 1.1.1.1, malware blocking 1.1.1.2, malware and adult content 1.1.1.3) - best for travelers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloudflare is very easy to setup.  Use the IP address that matches your use case.  These settings can carry over when you are away from home if you change them on your device.  There&amp;rsquo;s also an app that provides this service no matter where you are (just for mobile with Windows and Mac coming soon).  Cloudflare has good settings for most cases, is easy to setup, and has the mobile apps, but lacks the customization of OpenDNS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.quad9.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/quad9-logo-white@2x.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Quad9&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;quad9-9999&#34;&gt;Quad9 (9.9.9.9)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quad9 provides a service that is very similar to Cloudflare 1.1.1.2 - just set the DNS and forget it and it provides DNS with malicious sites blocked.  My experience with Quad9 has been largely indistinguishable from Cloudflare or OpenDNS with default settings, when testing blocking or response speed.  However, Quad9 doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the customization of OpenDNS or the apps that Cloudflare has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;google-8888&#34;&gt;Google (8.8.8.8)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a popular alternative for the geek set for a long time.  It&amp;rsquo;s easy to remember and it provides an &amp;ldquo;unfiltered&amp;rdquo; response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using one of these services helps to protect your home.  I use OpenDNS at home and have customized it to filter out a range of categories.  It doesn&amp;rsquo;t block everything on the Internet, but it addresses some of the obvious sites and it helps prevent &amp;ldquo;oops&amp;rdquo; experiences.  It seems to help with advertising too.  I use Cloudflare on my office network and it does a great job as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve benefitted from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nextpertise.net/ReasonablySecureBrowsing&#34;&gt;Reasonably Secure Browsing&lt;/a&gt; discussion, this is another &amp;ldquo;reasonable&amp;rdquo; step that you can take to improve your families Internet experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reasonably Secure Browsing</title>
      <link>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/200805_reasonablysecurebrowsing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 11:23:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/200805_reasonablysecurebrowsing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most of my articles are aimed at helping me remember how I did something &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt; years later, and helping other people who share my interest and want to solve similar problems.  This one is a little different.  When I speak to non-technical folks - at church, other parents, or within my family - I&amp;rsquo;m disappointed with the lack of understanding about computer security.  I was going to say &amp;ldquo;surprised&amp;rdquo;, but sadly I&amp;rsquo;m not.  This article tries to fix that by introducing this audience to concepts in Secure Browsing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get that we can&amp;rsquo;t all be aware of &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt;.  For instance, I&amp;rsquo;m not really interested in cars.  Still, if you are participating in an area (driving a car or browsing the web), then there&amp;rsquo;s a basic level of awareness that is needed and that you should aim for.  So this post is written for the non-technical in order to provide that grounding.  I&amp;rsquo;ll try to keep this up to date (pay attention to the posting date!) and I&amp;rsquo;ll start pointing people who ask those questions to this resource.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/0/09/Timmcgee.jpg#floatleft&#34; alt=&#34;Tim McGee from NCIS&#34;&gt;
I need to define &amp;ldquo;reasonable&amp;rdquo; before I get started.  Internet paranoia comes in three flavors - fear of malicious actors, fear of giant companies assembling dossiers to feed into marketing, and Orwellian fears about nation-states.  All three are reasonable things to be concerned about but this post only addresses the first.  Hiding from the NSA is beyond the ability of most people - even if they unplug.  Hiding from creepy companies is possible, but requires foregoing a lot of services that most of us are loathe to do without.  However, there are small steps that you can take that will give you a good degree of protection against maliciousness.  Reasonable means simple steps picking up bad code or leaking sensitive personal information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, what makes me think I&amp;rsquo;m an expert?  Well, I have a Master&amp;rsquo;s in Information Security and I&amp;rsquo;ve worked in IT operations and security for many, many years.  I&amp;rsquo;m no Tim McGee, but I get by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-safe-browsing-advice&#34;&gt;General safe-browsing advice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;If possible, run Linux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup your home to use OpenDNS or CloudFlare Family DNS servers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check for browser updates regularly, and apply them.  Keep plugins up to date as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Anti-Virus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t &lt;strong&gt;ever&lt;/strong&gt; click on links in email.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a secure password, and don’t re-use passwords between sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not save passwords within the browser. Use a password safe and subscribe to &lt;strong&gt;Have I been Pwned?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use SSL – Sites that use “HTTPS:” instead of “HTTP” are encrypting your traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a solution to monitor your bank accounts and credit reports.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-browser-checklist&#34;&gt;General Browser checklist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not save passwords in the browser.  Use a password safe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not use autofill.  Sites use hidden fields to send more than you think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have the browser ask you where to save files.  This alerts you to files being downloaded and allows you to cancel or put them in a folder for latter consideration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable click-to-play for plugins.  This will speed up the browser and allow you to decide when to use useful but potentially dangerous plugins like JavaScript, Flash, and Silverlight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not accept third-party cookies except by exception.  Clear all cookies after each session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Do Not Track.  This is more aimed at commercial privacy, and depends on the server honoring the request, but why not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be cautious using extensions, however there are a few that are suggested:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AdBlock Plus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTTPS Everywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refer to the following sections for specific help with your browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;chromehttpswwwmozillaorgmediaprotocolimglogosfirefoxbrowserlogo-lg-high-resfbc7ffbb50fdpngfloatright-chrome&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.mozilla.org/media/protocol/img/logos/firefox/browser/logo-lg-high-res.fbc7ffbb50fd.png#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Chrome&#34;&gt; Chrome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settings are found under the “stacked dots” icon on the right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under “set up sync”
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose “encrypt all synced data with your sync password”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uncheck Autofill and Passwords.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select advanced options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Privacy, check “protect you and your device from dangerous sites” and “send Do Not Track”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Passwords and Forms, uncheck both options (do not autofill or remember passwords).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Downloads, check “Ask where to save each file before downloading”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Plugins, select “Let me choose when to run plugin content”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Cookies, block third-party cookies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add recommended Extensions and remove un-needed ones.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AdBlock Plus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTTPS Everywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;firefoxhttpsp1hiclipartcompreview4981015635mozilla-sleek-icons-firefox-256x256-mozilla-firefox-logo-png-clipartjpgfloatright-firefox&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://p1.hiclipart.com/preview/498/1015/635/mozilla-sleek-icons-firefox-256x256-mozilla-firefox-logo-png-clipart.jpg#floatright&#34; alt=&#34;Firefox&#34;&gt; Firefox&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Options are found under the “hamburger” icon on the right.  In the drop down menu, select preferences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;em&gt;Files and Applications&lt;/em&gt; and select “Always ask me where to save files.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under &lt;em&gt;Network Settings&lt;/em&gt; select the settings button.  Choose &lt;strong&gt;enable DNS over HTTPS&lt;/strong&gt; and set it to Cloudflare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under &lt;em&gt;Privacy &amp;amp; Security&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the Standard Tracking Protection option and “Always apply Do Not Track”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set third-party cookies to delete when Firefox is closed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Logins and Passwods, disable &amp;ldquo;ask to save&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Forms and Autofill, disable Autofill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Permissions, check &amp;ldquo;Warn me when sites try to install an add-on&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Block pop-up windows&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disable Firefox data collection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Security, choose to Block dangerous and deceptive content, block dangerous downloads, and warn about unwanted software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back to the hamburger menu and select &lt;em&gt;Add Ons&lt;/em&gt;.  Remove any extensions you don&amp;rsquo;t need and add these two.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AdBlock Plus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTTPS Everywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;internet-explorer&#34;&gt;Internet Explorer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t use Internet Explorer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-browsers---&#34;&gt;Other browsers . . .&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some other browsers that are marketed as &amp;ldquo;secure&amp;rdquo;.  Examples include Avast, AVG, and Comodo.  My experience is that these are just custom versions of Chrome.  It&amp;rsquo;s difficult to keep up with all the customizations these different groups make, but generally I find that they are based on an older version of Chromium and aren&amp;rsquo;t always transparent about what changes they are making.  They tend to be updated less often and sometimes behave in unexpected ways because of the changes.  I do not recommend these today, but I&amp;rsquo;m open to the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another set of browsers attempt to compete more directly with Firefox and Chrome.  These include names like Brave and Opera.  I have a good opinion of both these options, but they are more common with power users and not really in scope of this guide.  Safari is used on Macs and is quite good.  I&amp;rsquo;ll try to add it in at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
